<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd">
  
<article lang="en">
  <articleinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Markus</firstname>
      <surname>Brückner</surname>
    </author>
    <title>yeanpypa &ndash; YEt ANother PYthon PArser framework</title>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Yeanpypa is a framework written in <ulink
        url="http://www.python.org/">Python</ulink> and heavily
        inspired by tools like <ulink
        url="http://pyparsing.sourceforge.net/">pyparsing</ulink> and
        <ulink
        url="http://www.boost.org/libs/spirit/index.html">boost::spirit</ulink>. It
        can be used to contruct recursive-descent parsers directly in
        python in a nearly "natural" way, meaning that the necessary
        Python source code looks much like the original EBNF that
        defined the grammar.
      </para>
    </abstract>      
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This section shows how to get and install yeanpypa, how to use
      it in own programs and gives some simple (and less simple) usage
      examples.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Getting &amp; installing yeanpypa</title>
      <para>
        Yeanpypa can be fetched directly from the Subversion
        repository at <ulink
        url="https://vcs.slash-me.net/snippets/yeanpypa/" />. Get the
        file <filename>yeanpypa.py</filename> and copy it into your
        Python distribution (normally in some place like
        <filename>/usr/lib/python2.4/</filename> under Linux, see your
        distribution's documentation for further details).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using yeanpypa</title>
      <para>
        First of all: construct an <ulink
        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EBNF">EBNF</ulink> grammar
        for the language you'd like to parse. A short example for
        parsing floating point numbers in C:
        <example>
          <title>An example of an EBNF for parsing floating point
          numbers</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
digit  ::= "1" | "2" | "3" | "4" | "5" | "6" | "7" | "9" | "0" ;
number ::= digit+ ;
float  ::= [ number ] "." number ;
          ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        This example defines a digits as one of the set from 0 to 9, a
        number as at least one digit and a floating point number as an
        optional number, followed by a dot, followed by a number.
        <note><para>This definition isn't totally correct as it would
        allow constructions like "0002.00". For simplicities sake,
        we'll go with it.</para></note> 
        In order to construct a yeanpypa-grammar from the EBNF, we
        write:
        <example>
          <title>yeanpypa representation of the floating point
          parser</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
          from yeanpypa import *

digit     = Literal('1') | Literal('2') | Literal('3') | Literal('4') | \
            Literal('5') | Literal('6') | Literal('7') | Literal('8') | \
            Literal('9') | Literal('0')
number    = Word(digit)
float_num = Optional(number) + Literal('.') + number
          ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        <note><para>In order to save typing, yeanpypa already provides
        a set of abstractions. The whole <varname>digit</varname>
        thing for example could be left out, as it is already provided
        by yeanpypa.</para></note>
        The resulting <varname>float_num</varname> object can be used
        to parse a floating point number like this:
        <example>
          <title>Using a parser object</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
result = parse(float_num, '123.123')
if result.full():
    print result.getTokens()
else:
    print 'The parser did not consume all input.'
          ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        This will print the following:
        <screen>['123', '.', '123']</screen>
        The parser validated the input and created a list of token
        according to the grammar specification. 
      </para>
      <para>
        In order to use the token, we can ignore the dot, as it does
        not tell us anything apart from the fact that we saw a
        floating point number (which we know because of the validation
        anyway). That's where <command>hide()</command> comes into
        play. The <command>hide()</command> method of a rule (the
        basic building block of a grammar) tells the parser to ignore
        any token created by the rule. We change the grammar like
        this:
        <example>
          <title>Floating point parser ignoring the dot</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
number    = Word(digit)
float_num = Optional(number) + Literal('.').hide() + number
          ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        <note><para>We removed the <varname>digit</varname>
        declaration and rather use the abstraction provided by
        yeanpypa.</para></note>
        Note the <command>hide()</command>-call at the
        <command>Literal(...)</command>-rule. This instructs the
        parser to ignore the token created by that rule (i.e. the '.')
        and not create any output.
      </para>
      <para>
        Using this parser yields the following output:
        <screen>['123', '123']</screen>
        We have successfully eliminated the superfluous dot token from
        the output.
      </para>
      <para>
        As we're parsing numbers, we would like to see the token as
        actual numbers instead of strings representing
        numbers. Yeanpypa provides the tools to transform the strings
        while matching using a semantic action:
        <example>
          <title>Floating point parser using semantic actions</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
number    = Word(digit).setAction(lambda x: int(x[0]))
float_num = Optional(number) + Literal('.').hide() + number
          ]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        We have attached a semantic action to the
        <varname>number</varname>-rule, which transforms its input
        from a string into an integer. The action is called when the
        rule sucessfully matches and gets a list of token generated by
        that rule. The function must return a list of token
        representing the desired output of the parser. This may be the
        original input list (in case the action merely outputs some
        debug information or generates some external data structure)
        or it may be a transformed token (list) as in the example
        given.
      </para>
      <para>
        Using this version of the parser yields the following output:
        <screen>[123, 123]</screen>        
        As you can see, the result token list now contains two
        integers instead of string representing them.
        <note><para>Attaching an action to a rule where
        <command>hide()</command> was called causes the action to be
        executed, but the output to be thrown away. Keep that in mind
        if you intend to mix these two facilities.</para></note>
        <note><para>An action called for a subrule will
        <emphasis>NOT</emphasis> be notified if the containing rule
        fails at a later stage. E.g. if the first
        <varname>number</varname> rule in the above example matched,
        but <varname>float_num</varname> failed due to a missing dot,
        the action of the first <varname>number</varname> would
        already have been called and would not be notified about the
        failure. Keep that in mind when constructing external data
        structures using semantic actions.</para></note>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
